Okay, today's דף *daf* is כ"ט *Chaf Tet*, קידושין *Kiddushin* 29, and
we pick up in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* and we are now
moving away from issues relating to קניינים *kinyanim*, but because the משניות
*mishnayot* have been dealing with like all these categories, very well organized
into different types of קניינים *kinyanim* and then כל הנעשה דמים באחר
*kol hanaseh damim be'acher* and רשות גבוה *reshut gavoah*, so we're going
to deal with other types of ways of categorizing moving on actually
to מצוות mitzvos *mitzvot* and this משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* is very rich
and has a lot of important major מצוות *mitzvot* categories here. So
let's take a look. The משנה Mishnah. כ"ט עמוד א' *Mishnah Chaf
Tet Amud Aleph*. כל מצוות הבן על al, האב, אנשים חייבין ונשים
פטורות *Kol mitzvot haben al ha'av, anashim chayavin venashim peturot*. All the
מצוות *mitzvot* of the child on the father, men are obligated and
women are exempt. So this is a very strange locution, the same
way the earlier משנה *Mishnah* כל הנעשה דמים באחר *kol hanaseh damim
be'acher* or רשות גבוה בכסף רשות הדיוט *reshut gavoah bekesef reshut hedyot*—these
really indicate very early משניות *mishnayot*, some of these more stranger formulations.
So all of the מצוות *mitzvot* of the child on the father,
men are obligated and women are exempt. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says what that means is that all of the מצוות *mitzvot* that
relate to the child that a parent is obligated to do towards
his child, those are מצוות *mitzvot* of a father towards their son,
they are not מצוות *mitzvot* of a mother towards her daughter or
a mother towards her son or a father towards her daughter. The
parental מצוות *mitzvot* towards their child are men are obligated and women
are exempt. וכל מצוות האב על הבן, אחד אנשים ואחד נשים חייבין
*Vechol mitzvot ha'av al haben, echad anashim ve'echad nashim chayavin*. All מצוות
*mitzvot* of the father that relate to the child, all children's obligations
towards their parents, which is basically the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of כיבוד
אב ואם *kibbud av va'em*, אחד אנשים ואחד נשים חייבין *echad anashim
ve'echad nashim chayavin*, whether men or women are obligated, both boys and
girls or men and women, adult children are also obligated, are obligated
to honor both their male and female parents. So parental obligations towards
children is fathers to sons, children's obligations towards parents is boys and
girls, men and women towards fathers and mothers. וכל מצוות עשה שהזמן
גרמה *Vechol mitzvot asseh shehazman grama*, now a one that is very
well known, all positive מצוות *mitzvot* that are time-bound or time causes
it—interesting questions of exactly how you find הזמן גרמה *hazman grama*—אנשים חייבין
ונשים פטורות *anashim chayavin venashim peturot*, men are obligated and women are
exempt. רמב"ם *Rambam* already points out there are about as many exceptions
to this rule as there are cases that satisfy the rule. There
are some that are time-bound that women are obligated, there are some
that are not time-bound that women are exempt, like תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah. *Talmud Torah*. Anyway, this is the category, the rule that is
given, and it's always a question whether this rule is really the
rule that is descriptive after we know all the particulars or whether
this rule really dictates which are the מצוות *mitzvot* positive מצוות *mitzvot*
that men are obligated and women are exempt. Okay, but that's the
idea of time-bound מצוות *mitzvot*. וכל מצוות עשה שלא הזמן גרמה *Vechol
mitzvot asseh shelo hazman grama*, but all positive מצוות *mitzvot* that are
not time-bound or caused by time, אחד אנשים ואחד נשים חייבין *echad
anashim ve'echad nashim chayavin*, whether men and women are equally obligated. וכל
מצוות לא תעשה *Vechol mitzvot lo ta'aseh*, all negative commandments, בין שהזמן
גרמה בין שלא הזמן גרמה *bein shehazman grama bein shelo hazman grama*,
whether they are time-bound or not, like שבת *Shabbat* is time-bound, not
eating חזיר *chazir* is not, אחד אנשים ואחד נשים חייבין *echad anashim
ve'echad nashim chayavin*, men and women are equally obligated. חוץ *Chutz*, the
one case that women are exempt, or three cases, מבל תקיף *mibal
takif*, not to cut off the פאות *payot* of the head, ובל
תשחית *u'val tashchit*, not to destroy the corners of the beard, ובל
תטמא למתים *u'val titama lametim*, and not to become impure to the
dead, which applies to male כהנים kohanim, *kohanim*. Okay, so those now
we saw bring our categorization and organization that has sort of been
the driving force of all these משניות *mishnayot* now to the world
of מצוות *mitzvot*. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
מאי כל מצוות הבן על האב *Mai kol mitzvot haben al ha'av*?
What does this mean, all the מצוות *mitzvot* of the son on
the father? אילימא כל מצוות דמיחייב ברא למיעבד לאבא *Elima kol mitzvot
demichayev bera lemivad le'abba*, if it means the מצוות *mitzvot* the son,
the child is obligated to do towards the father, towards the parent,
so נשים פטורות *nashim peturot*, women are exempt? So what is the
obligation primarily directed towards parents? That's כיבוד אב ואם *kibbud av va'em*.
But that can't be, ותניא *vetanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *braita*:
איש *Ish*—this is the פסוק *pasuk*—איש אמו ואביו תיראו *ish immo ve'aviv
tirau*, each man shall fear his mother and father. So the מדרש
כהנים kohanim, *Midrash Kohanim* says—the מדרש תנאים *Midrash Tannaim* says—אין לי אלא
איש *ein li ela ish*, I only know a man is obligated
in fearing parents and honoring parents. אשה מנין *Ishah minayin*, how do
I know a woman? כשהוא אומר איש אמו ואביו תיראו *keshehu omer
ish immo ve'aviv tirau*, when it says you shall fear in the
plural, they shall fear, הרי כאן שנים *harei kan shenayim*, it's talking
about two, so it doesn't just mean a man, it means in
the plural, so men and women are equally obligated in fearing their
parents and in honoring their parents. So it cannot be that obligations
towards parents is limited to men. אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר *Amar
Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar*, here is how you have to read the
משנה *Mishnah*: כל מצוות הבן המוטלות עליו *Kol mitzvot haben hamutallot alav*,
all the obligations, the מצוות *mitzvot* that relate to your children that
are the parental obligations towards their children, מצוות הבן *mitzvot haben*. obligations
towards children parental obligations לעשות לבנו אנשים חייבים ונשים פטורות anashim chayavim
venashim p'turos men are obligated and women are exempt. Now this is
talking about men as parents, fathers are obligated women are not, but
also you know as we'll see it also winds up relating to
sons as opposed to daughters. Okay, and now what is included in
that? So there'll be a whole list. דתנינא להא דתנו רבנן Detanina
leha detanu rabanan we taught in the בריתא Braisah what we taught
what we taught in our משנה what we taught in the בריתא.
Braisah. האב חייב בבנו למולו Ha'av chayav bivno lemolo the father's obligation
towards his son is to do a ברית מילה bris milah on
the father towards the son ולפדותו ulefiddoso פדיון הבן pidyon haben also
only on the son and here telling us also only on the
father. וללמדו תורה ulilamedo Torah to teach him תורה Torah ולהשיאו אשה
ulehashio ishah and to marry him off to a woman? That's interesting,
that does not seem to be a biblical מצוה mitzvah. but okay
nobody said we're limiting ourselves to biblical. וללמדו אומנות ulilamedo ummanus and
to teach him a trade also does not seem to be a
biblical one but okay a דרבנן drabbanan מצוה. ויש אומרים אף להשיטו
במים veyesh omrim af lehashito bamayim also to teach him how to
swim which used to be a requirement for graduating college in case
you would you know be in a boat and it would capsize
or something or sink you should be able to swim it's a
survival ability to you know have basic survival techniques. רבי יהודה אומר
כל שאינו מלמד את בנו אומנות מלמדו ליסטות Rabbi Yehuda omer kol
she'eino melamed es bno ummanus melamdo listus anybody who does not teach
his son a trade is as if he teaches him you know
banditry to be a robber. So the גמרא Gemara says ליסטות סלקא
דעתך listus salka dachach you really teaching him to be a robber?
I mean you're not teaching him a trade but you're not teaching
him the trade of being a robber so or a highwayman. אלא
כאילו מלמדו ליסטות ela ke'ilu melamdo listus it's as if you did
that because since you're not giving him a legitimate way of earning
a living a legal way of earning a living he will go
ahead and make you know earn money well not earn money whatever
anyway he will go ahead and have to rob and steal in
order to in order to I mean you know make any gainful
earning of money. So that's the that's that which is interesting why
the בריתא Braisah had to say this you know oh it's so
bad it's as if you taught him banditry I mean if it's
an obligation it's an obligation but apparently there was a need to
underscore you know that obligation maybe people were not taking it as
seriously as they needed to so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda had to
give that little this little like moral prod of that it'll be
like you're teaching him how to be a robber. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara is going to unpack this בריתא Braisah with all
these different obligations of the father on the child. It's interesting to
point out that it's not listed in this משנה the general obligation
of חינוך chinuch you know teaching a child to do the מצוות
to say the ברכות brachos to put on ציצית tzitzis to put
on תפילין tefillin to shake a לולב lulav you know light candles
all the all the general ideas of חינוך chinuch and the חינוך
chinuch about the negative ones. Here too in other sources it's indicated
that that's really the father's obligation although there is some discussion whether
that is also the mother's obligation but the emphasis of that also
very much seems to be on the father. Okay let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara as we go through these. למולו Lemolo
to circumcise him to do a ברית מילה bris milah מנלן menalan
how do you know that's a father's obligation? דכתיב וימל אברהם את
יצחק בנו Dechsiv Vayammol Avraham es Yitzchak bno Avraham gave the ברית
מילה bris milah to Yitzchak his son so you see Avraham. והיכא
Veheicha now we're going to see in a minute how we know
that's the הלכה halacha for future generations. והיכא דלא מליה אבוה מיחייבי
בי דינא למימליה Veheicha dila malye avuha mechayvei bei dina lemimalye now
the גמרא Gemara digresses a little and says okay we've established father's
obligation by the way if the father has not done it the
obligation reverts to the בית דין. beis din. It becomes a communal
obligation. בית דין Beis din represents the community דכתיב dechsiv it says
המול לכם כל זכר Himmol lachem kol zachar you shall have circumcised
for you all male so that's talking to you the collective you
as a Jewish community have to ensure that all the males among
you are circumcised so
if the father isn't doing it the obligation
reverts to the community. Okay now והיכא
דלא מליה בי דינא veheicha dila malye bei dina now if בית
דין beis din didn't do it when he was young and now
this boy becomes an adult מיחייב איהו למימהל נפשיה mechayev ihu lemimhal
nafshei now he's obligated to give himself a
ברית מילה bris milah דכתיב וערל זכר אשר לא ימול בשר ערלתו
ונכרתה dechsiv ve'arel zachar asher lo yimmol besar orlaso venichresa and an
uncircumcised male who does not have his foreskin you know circumcised he
shall be cut off. So since he is being punished by being
cut off he obviously has the obligation. ואשר לא ימול ve'asher lo
yimmol if he doesn't do it circumcise himself means he now has
the obligation to circumcise himself if it was not done for him.
I should mention since this is about the mother that it does
not say it goes from father to community it doesn't say that
if the father isn't doing it it becomes the mother's obligation. It
seems like a mother isn't even a backup or secondary to a
father. There's a רש"י Rashi elsewhere and a מראה אור זרוע Mareh
Or Zarua that indicates that actually the mother is obligated if the
father isn't doing it raises interesting questions about cases of like a
single mother having a child can she say the ברכה bracha להכניסו
בבריתו של אברהם אבינו lehachniso bivriso shel Avraham Avinu acting as her
own as a mother qua mother or at least acting as representing
the community in the place of בית דין. beis din. Anyway it
is interesting here again that the mother seems to be cut out
even from a backup. Secondary role, but that is somewhat of a
question. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara,
continues, ואיהי, V'eehee, so that's how we know the father is obligated.
Now, איהי מנלן דלא מחייבא, Eehee minalan d'lo michayva,
how do you know that she is not obligated? Maybe he is,
but how do you know she's not? דכתיב Dichsiv כאשר צוה אתו
אלהים, Kaasher tziva oso Elohim,
like God commanded him Abraham, אתו ולא אותה, Oso v'lo osa, only
him, not her, not Sarah. אשכחן מיד Ashkachan miyad ודורות מנלן? V'doros
minalan? So that's in terms of that generation, of Abraham and Sarah.
How do you know that's the model for future generations? תנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל, Tana d'vei Rabi Yishmael, they taught in the school of
Rabbi Ishmael, כל מקום שנאמר צו אינו אלא זירוז מיד ולדורות. Kol
makom shenemar tzav eino ela zeirus miyad ul'doros. When it says צו,
tzav, it means צו, tzav, command, it means that God is giving
encouragement, you know, do it with alacrity, and he's saying also for
future generations. זירוז Zeirus דכתיב Dichsiv וצו את יהושע וחזקהו ואמצהו, V'tzav
es Yehoshua v'chazkeihu v'amtzeihu, we just read last week's פרשה, parsha, command
Joshua, strengthen him and give him courage. So you know you have
to give him encouragement and you know and and and prodding. מיד
ולדורות מנלן? Miyad ul'doros minalan? How do you know for future generations?
דכתיב Dichsiv מן היום אשר צוה ה' והלאה לדורותיכם, Min hayom asher
tziva Hashem v'halah l'doroseichem, from the day that God commanded you and
for future generations. So assuming that what's true in those two פסוקים
psukim about צו tzav is true all the times it says צו,
tzav, so this commandment to Abraham, כאשר צוה אתו, kaasher tziva oso,
the צוה tziva future generations is only for the father, not for
the mother. That's how you know ברית מילה. Bris Milah. לפדותו, Lifdoso,
how about
פדיון הבן? Pidyon Haben? מנלן? Minalan? דכתיב Dichsiv כל בכור בניך תפדה,
Kol bechor banecha tifdeh, all the firstborn of your children you shall
you shall redeem. והיכא דלא פרקיה אבוה, V'heicha d'lo purkeih avuha, but
now we're going to see in a minute how we know it
excludes women. You shall... how do you know it excludes women?
And but now we're going to also digress and say what if
the father isn't doing his obligation? מחייב איהו למיפרקיה
לנפשיה, Michayiv eehu l'mifreikeih l'nafsheih, he has to redeem himself. דכתיב Dichsiv
פדה תפדה, Padoh sifdeh, okay, that you shall surely redeem. So that
is coming to tell you that you know he has to do
it himself if it is not being done for him. Now what
you will notice is is that it does not say that בית
דין Beis Din is obligated because as opposed to uncircumcised males where
there's a communal obligation that all the males are circumcised, right, that
has to do with Jewish identity and so on for men, there
is not a communal obligation that all the men be redeemed, all
the firstborn be redeemed. That is an obligation on the father and
if not on the father, then on the child himself when he
becomes an adult.
ואיהי מנלן דלא מיפקדה? V'eehee minalan d'lo mifkida? How do you know
a woman is not obligated? דכתיב Dichsiv תפדה תיפדה, Tifdeh tipadeh, you
read it as or you know you read it
as תפדה tifdeh and like and
תיפדה, tipadeh, which means both you shall redeem and you shall be
redeemed, okay, so that play on words. So what does that tell
us? The one who's doing the redeeming also has to be the
one who's in a position to be a redeemed, the redeemer has
to be able to be redeemed. כל שמצווה לפדות את עצמו מצווה
לפדות את אחרים, Kol shemitzveh lifdos es atzmo mitzveh lifdos es acherim,
anybody who is obligated to redeem himself
can be obligated to redeem others. וכל שאינו מצווה לפדות את עצמו,
V'chol she'eino mitzveh lifdos es atzmo, somebody who is not obligated to
redeem themselves, a woman who is not somebody... it says בכור בניך,
bechor banecha, your... as we'll see, בניך ולא בנותיך, banecha v'lo bnosecha,
your sons, so therefore, the same way a woman is not the
one who is redeemed, because we'll find out that redeemed means sons,
she is not the one who is obligated to ensure that her
son gets redeemed. וכל שאינו מצווה לפדות את עצמו אינו מצווה לפדות
אחרים. V'chol she'eino mitzveh lifdos es atzmo eino mitzveh lifdos acherim. Okay,
but now we have to clarify this. How do you know a
woman is not obligated herself to be
redeemed? ואיהי מנלן דלא מחייבא V'eehee minalan d'lo michayva למיפרק נפשה l'mifrak
nafshah to redeem herself? דכתיב Dichsiv
תפדה תיפדה, Tifdeh tipadeh, so it says you shall redeem, you shall
be redeemed. כל שהאחרים מצווים לפדותו מצווה לפדות את עצמו, Kol she'acherim
mtzuvim lifdoso mitzveh lifdos es atzmo, if other people have to obligate
have to redeem you, you have to redeem yourself. וכל שאין האחרים
מצווים לפדותו אינו מצווה לפדות את עצמו, V'chol she'ein acherim mtzuvim lifdoso
eino mitzveh lifdos es atzmo, if nobody else is obligated to redeem
you... this child's obligation to redeem himself is when the parent does
not fulfill their obligation. So if a parent isn't obligated to redeem,
the child isn't obligated to redeem themselves. Let's get to the end
of this chain and then I'll unravel it and explain it. את
עצמו. Atzmo. ומניין שאין האחרים מצווים לפדותה? Uminayin she'ein acherim mtzuvim lifdosah?
How do you know other people don't have to redeem a girl?
דאמר קרא D'amar kra כל בכור בניך תפדה, Kol bechor banecha tifdeh,
all the firstborn of your sons you shall redeem, בניך ולא בנותיך,
banecha v'lo bnosecha, sons and not daughters. So this is a three
stage part, it's easier to work from the end and go backwards.
We learn from בניך ולא בנותיך banecha v'lo bnosecha that girls are
not obligated to be redeemed by their parents. Once that's true, we
learn by תפדה תיפדה tifdeh tipadeh that somebody who is not obligated
to be redeemed by others, girls who are not obligated to be
redeemed by their parents, are not obligated to redeem themselves. The child's
obligation to redeem himself is only when the parent does not fulfill
the obligation. So since girls are not obligated to be redeemed by
their parents, they're not obligated to redeem themselves. And then we do
תפדה תיפדה tifdeh tipadeh the other way, somebody who's not obligated to
redeem themselves. selves, a girl, a woman, is not obligated to redeem
others, to redeem the sons. So in short, because only a son
is the redeem is the one who is redeemed, then that means
that the obligation is only on fathers and only on boys, not
on mothers, not on daughters. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis
taught.
Okay. הוא לפדות ובנו לפדות. Hu lifdot u'vno lifdot. הוא קודם לבנו.
Hu kodem livno. If you have to decide between should I redeem
myself or redeem my son? So, you know, you have to take
care of your obligation towards yourself before that towards your son. Which
is interesting cause it's like on one hand, it only came upon
you yourself because your father did not take care of it. On
the other hand, this is about my own personal status, and I
was obligated to take care of my own status anyway before I
had a child, before I had a son. So therefore, the first
position is you come first. רבי יהודה אומר בנו קודמו. Rabbi Yehuda
omer bno kodmo. No, your son comes first. שזה מצותו על אביו.
Shezeh mitzvato al aviv. This one, the son is the obligation on
the father, like the language of the משנה.
I'm sorry. שזה, Shezeh, excuse me, I said that wrong. This, the
father, his obligation for him to be redeemed originally was on his
father. Okay, וזה מצות בנו עליו. Vezeh mitzvat bno alav. But you,
if you're the father, your obligation of your son is on you.
Meaning, what he's saying is, okay, if we as we say אברהם,
Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and יעקב, Yaakov, okay, and we're talking here about
יצחק, Yitzchak, יצחק Yitzchak was to be redeemed by אברהם. Avraham. So
what he is saying is look, the primary obligation of יצחק Yitzchak
was on אברהם. Avraham. The primary obligation of יעקב Yaakov is on
יצחק. Yitzchak. So יצחק's Yitzchak primary obligation is to יעקב, Yaakov, and
his obligation to his son comes before his obligation to himself. Which
makes sense cause he only becomes obligated to himself because his father
did not fulfill his obligation. So that seems like a very nice
conceptual question. On the one hand, it's yourself, on the other hand,
it started with your father. So which comes first? But now the
גמרא Gemara like reframes it. אמר רבי ירמיהו. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyahu. אמר
רבי ירמיהו. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyahu. הכל מודים. Hakol modim. Everybody agrees. כל
היכא דליכא אלא חמש סלעים. Kol heicha deleka ela chamesh s'loim. If
all you have is the five סלעים s'loim for פדיון הבן, pidyon
haben, which seems to be what we're talking about, הוא קודם לבנו.
hu kodem livno. That you come first. Which is not at all
what it sounded like, but okay. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? מצוה
דגופיה עדיפא. Mitzva degufey adifa. Yeah, forget this question of derivative or
whatever. Your obligation, your taking care of yourself comes before your obligation
towards taking care of your son. We could also say that chronologically
it came presumably before your son was born. Okay. כי פליגי היכא
דאיכא חמש משועבדים וחמש בני חורין. Ki peligi heicha de'ika chamesh meshubadim
vechamesh bnei chorin. The question is that you have ten סלעים, s'loim,
right? פדיון הבן pidyon haben is five סלעים. s'loim. Five in the
bank, five cash. Five, it's property, but really it is, you know,
it's other people have a lien on it. Creditors have a lien
on this other
property. Okay.
So what are you going to do? So let's take a look.
Okay. רבי יהודה סבר מלוה הכתובה בתורה ככתובה בשטר דמיא. Rabbi Yehuda
savar milveh haktuva baTorah kaktuva bishtar damya. If a loan written in
the תורה, Torah, an obligation exists in the תורה Torah is like
it's written in a שטר, shtar, means that there are liens on
it. So I have a plot of land worth five סלעים. s'loim.
And I had that since I was בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, and
because I'm obligated to redeem myself, so כהנים, kohanim the collective of
כהנים, kohanim as it were, has a lien on that piece of
land because I owe them five סלעים. s'loim. Then I came along
because מלוה הכתובה בתורה ככתובה בשטר דמיא. milveh haktuva baTorah kaktuva bishtar
damya. I came along and I borrowed some money from a creditor
ראובן, Reuven, and now ראובן Reuven has a lien on that land.
But the lien of the כהנים Kohanim came first. So what do
I do? So בהני חמש פריק ליה בריה. Behani chamesh parik lei
brei. So I take five
and
I go ahead and I redeem my son with this five that
is cash. Okay. So where were we? ופריק ליה בריה. Uparik lei
brei.
בהני חמש פריק ליה בריה. Behani chamesh parik lei brei. ואזא כהן
וטריף ליה לחמש משועבדים לדידיה. Ve'aza kohen vetarif lei lechamesh meshubadim lidiidey.
And then as far as the five to redeem myself, remember that
the כהן kohen had a lien on it from the time, you
know, I was בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah or something. So therefore, he
takes that away from the people that have the, people I borrowed
money from, from ראובן, Reuven, because ראובן's Reuven lien came later than
the כהנים's Kohanim lien. So it doesn't seem very fair to ראובן,
Reuven, but the way רש"י Rashi explains it is look, I have
five cash. I could give it for myself and that would be
nice to ראובן, Reuven, then ראובן's Reuven lien on the land would
be protected. But I'm actually entitled because of the way רש"י Rashi
frames this, תוספות Tosafot has a different way of reading this גמרא,
Gemara I'm entitled to give it for the פדיון pidyon of my
son because my obligation to my son comes first,
I give it for my son, and then it just so happens
that ראובן, Reuven, sorry ראובן, Reuven, you're out, the כהנים Kohanim had
an earlier lien, and that way everybody gets satisfied. Okay, so when
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually says that according to this, that my
son comes first, it really doesn't mean my son and not me,
it means I give to my son first and that lets the,
and that lets the כהנים collect the, the liens and to collect
their payment for myself as well. ורבנן סברי, V'Rabbanan savri, and the
Rabbis are of the
opinion, מלווה הכתובה בתורה לאו ככתובה בשטר דמיא, milveh hakesuvah baTorah lav
kikesuvah bishtar damya, if it's written in the Torah it's not like
it's written in a שטר, shtar, והלכך מצוות דגופיה עדיף, v'hilkach mitzvas
degufayh adif, and therefore the כהנים don't have any lien and I
have to choose between myself and my son, so I'm going to
choose myself. Okay, so as you could see, this is a very
difficult read according to רש"י Rashi because, first of all, it doesn't
seem like we're being fair to ראובן, Reuven, and also for רש"י
Rashi to explain why I'm allowed to give the five in cash
to my son, he says because my son's obligation comes first, but
the whole point of this way of reading it is to emphasize
that my obligation to myself comes first. So תוספות Tosafos has a
different read. Anyway, it gets, makes things a little complicated. Bracketing this
interpretation in the גמרא Gemara and רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafos, the
simplest explanation is a very clean one. Is it clear that my
obligation to myself comes first, or do we say that no, my
obligation to myself started with my father? My primary obligation is to
my son. Much better way of reading it. Anyway, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. לפדות את בנו ולעלות לרגל.
Lifdos es beno v'la'alos laregel. Let's say I have only so much
cash on hand, and I can either use it to redeem my
son or to do עלייה לרגל. aliyah laregel. פודה את בנו ואחר
כך עולה לרגל. Podeh es beno v'achar kach oleh laregel. First you
redeem your son, then you are עולה לרגל. oleh laregel. רבי יהודה
אומר עולה לרגל ואחר כך פודה את בנו. Rabbi Yehuda omer oleh
laregel v'achar kach podeh es beno. This is a little ironic because
in the previous case רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said your obligation to
your son comes first, but here he's saying first you're עולה לרגל
oleh laregel and then you redeem your son. But now it's not,
you know, apples and oranges, so it's not a question of self
versus son, it's רגל regel versus
פדיון. pidyon. שזו מצוה עוברת וזו מצוה אינה עוברת, Shezu mitzvah overes
v'zu mitzvah einah overes, because רגל regel you can only do for
a limited period of time. You know, so later when you get
the money you'll do פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Right now if you
miss doing עלייה לרגל, aliyah laregel, you're not going to do עלייה
לרגל. aliyah laregel. So the גמרא Gemara likes that reason. בשלמא לרבי
יהודה כדי קאמר טעמא, Bishlama l'Rabbi Yehuda kidei ka'amar ta'ama, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says a good reason. אלא רבנן מאי טעמייהו, Ela Rabbanan
mai ta'amayhu, what's the reason of the Rabbis? דאמר קרא De'amar kra
כל בכור בניך תפדה, kol bechor banecha tifdeh, because just the order
of the פסוקים. pesukim. והדר ולא יראו פני ריקם. V'hadar v'lo yera'u
fanai reikam. The פסוקים pesukim juxtaposed them. First take care of your
son, then worry about עלייה לרגל. aliyah laregel. I'm sure something interesting
theologically could be said about this, but not one that occurs to
me right now. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. מניין שאם היו לו
חמישה בנים מחמש נשים שחייב לפדות את כולן? Minayin she'im hayu lo
chamishah banim mechamesh nashim shechayav lifdos es kulan? How do you know
if somebody had five firstborn from five different women or wives that
he has to redeem all of them? They're all firstborn to their
mother, not their father. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar כל בכור בניך תפדה,
kol bechor banecha tifdeh, all your firstborn sons you shall redeem. So
meaning you might have multiple firstborn sons. פשיטא, Pshita, isn't that obvious?
פטר רחם תלא רחמנא, Peter rechem tala Rachmana, the Torah says it's
about the one that opens up the womb, so it goes by
firstborn to the mother. מהו דתימא נילף בכור בכור מנחלה, Mahu d'teima
neilaf bechor bechor minachalah, I might think that there are two requirements:
it has to be firstborn to the mother, but we also learn
about the idea of firstborn when it comes to inheritance. מה להלן
ראשית אונו אף כאן ראשית אונו, Mah lahan reishis ono af kan
reishis ono, there it's the first of his strength, meaning firstborn of
the father. Here too? So maybe you have both? קא משמע לן,
Ka mashma lan, no, it only goes by firstborn of the mother.
Okay, so that's how we know מילה milah and פדיון הבן, pidyon
haben, those are the ones that we know are very much about
sons. The interesting thing is that mothers get written out, especially when
you consider the idea of ציפורה Tzipporah who did the ברית מילה
bris milah etc. Now it's worth pointing out that there's a difference
between who can execute the act—can a woman do the act of
ברית מילה? bris milah? It certainly sounds that way from the story
in ציפורה. Tzipporah. That's a discussion, an issue discussed in the גמרא
in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah as opposed to who is obligated to
see that it gets done. That's our question. Now, you know, mother,
is the mother also obligated? Of course the ציפורה Tzipporah story is
also ציפורה Tzipporah took the obligation to make sure it got done
as well. But anyway here mother is written out although as I
said there are some opinions that mother does have an obligation after
father, at least by ברית מילה. bris milah. Okay, now we get
to תורה. Torah. וללמדו תורה. V'lilmedo Torah. מנלן, Menalan, where do you
know this is only on fathers and sons? דכתיב ולמדתם אותם את
בניכם, Dechtiv v'limadtem osam es beneichem, you shall teach your sons. והיכא
דלא אגמריה אבוה, V'heicha d'lo agmreih avuh, if the father did not
teach, מיחייב איהו למיגמר נפשיה, mechayav ihu lemigmar nafsheih, you have to
teach yourself Torah. This is the obligation of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah,
If your parents did not teach you all the Torah there was
to learn, you have to teach yourself. דכתיב ולמדתם, Dechtiv ulimadtem,
not ולמדתם v'limadtem which is you shall teach, ולמדתם ulimadtem you shall
learn. ואיהי מנלן דלא מיחייבא, V'eehi menalan d'la mechayva, how do you
know, now it is interesting that the גמרא says that that seems
like if your father didn't do his job, I mean it's patterned
after the idea of פדיון הבן pidyon haben and ברית מילה, bris
milah, but of course how is a parent supposed to... teach child
the entire תורה Torah, *Torah*, you know, when does one fulfill the
מצוה *mitzvah* of teaching תורה Torah, *Torah* and also even if one
knows the entire תורה *Torah*, there's a מצוה *mitzvah* to just do
the act of learning, not necessarily to acquire more knowledge. So it
is a sort of a funny way of framing it maybe the
גמרא *Gemara* here refers to a certain base knowledge the parent has
to teach, but anyway, much larger discussion of exactly the מצוות *mitzvos*
associated with תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah*. Now, how do you know that
a woman is not obligated to educate her son? דכתיב *d'ksiv* ולמדתם
ולמדתם *v'limadetem u'lemadetem*, you shall teach, you shall learn. כל שמצווה ללמוד
מצווה ללמד *Kol she'metzuveh lilmod metzuveh lelamed*. If you have an obligation
to learn, you have an obligation to teach. וכל שאינו מצווה ללמוד
אינו מצווה ללמד *v'chol she'eino metzuveh lilmod eino metzuveh lelamed*. If you're
not obligated to learn, you're not obligated to teach. This is very
similar to what the גמרא *Gemara* did by פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen,
*pidyon haben* or by ברית מילה Brit Milah, *bris milah* also. ואי
מנלן דלא מיחייבא *v'i minalan d'lo michayva*? How do you know she's
not obligated to learn למילף נפשה *lemeylaf nafsha* to learn for herself?
דכתיב *d'ksiv* ולמדתם ולמדתם *v'limadetem u'lemadetem*. Same thing, it's going to be
a three-part sort of thing: you shall teach and you shall learn.
כל שהם מצווים ללמדו *Kol she'heim metzuvim lelamdo*, any time, if you're
obligated to be taught by others, אז מצווה ללמד את עצמו *az
metzuveh lelamed es atzmo*, you have to teach yourself. כל שאין הם
מצווים ללמדו *Kol she'ein heim metzuvim lelamdo*, if you're not obligated to
be taught by others, אין מצווה ללמד את עצמו *ein metzuveh lelamed
es atzmo*, you don't have to teach yourself. ומנלן דאין הם מצווים
ללמדה *u'minalan d'ein heim metzuvim lelamdah*? And how do you know others
don't have to teach a girl? דאמר קרא *d'amar kra* ולמדתם אותם
את בניכם *u'lemadetem osam es b'neichem*, teach your children, ולא בנותיכם *v'lo
b'noseichem*, not your daughters. Okay, so this is of course the famous
גמרא *Gemara* and this is of course and you know such a
major issue that started you know way back when in the 50s
or maybe even earlier, you know הרב סולובייצ'יק *Rav Soloveitchik* and on
the one hand and and the ליובאוויטשער רבי *Lubavitcher Rebbe* on the
other and you know הרב *Rav*... so many... in the in the
period of modernity, a response to this issue or a discussion around
this issue about really women's exemption from תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah*. But
just first to explain what the גמרא *Gemara* is saying is that
the גמרא *Gemara* is saying if we start with the assumption of
בניכם ולא בנותיכם *b'neichem v'lo b'noseichem*, sons and not daughters,
which clearly I think we could agree is פשט *pshat* by the
פדיון הבן *pidyon haben*, but and you know
but here also it's interesting some want to debate whether that's פשט
*pshat* here in the in the פסוקים *psukim* here, whether you know
whether that's specifically חז"ל's *Chazal's* read, but certainly in a very male-centric
type of a society, it's a it's a reasonable read. So if
we're going to read בניכם ולא בנותיכם *b'neichem v'lo b'noseichem*, sons and
not daughters, so daughters are not obligated to be educated by others,
therefore they're not obligated to teach themselves, and if they're not obligated
to teach themselves, they're not obligated to teach their sons. Okay, and
from all of this emerges women's exemption from תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah*.
Now of course you know going back to סוטה *Sotah*, you remember
there was a whole debate by הקהל *Hakhel* and the importance of
women actually also we just read it in the פרשה *parsha*, you
know everybody being gathered אנשים נשים והטף *anashim nashim v'hataf* and
and an interesting debate in תנאים *Tannaim* about whether it's a good
thing to teach women תורה *Torah* or not a good thing to
teach women תורה *Torah*.
And it's also worth noting how many times the תורה *Torah* in
דברים *Devarim* emphasizes that at מעמד הר סיני *Ma'amad Har Sinai* everybody
was there: men, women, and children. And the חז"ל *Chazal* make a
point, you know, כה תאמר לבית יעקב Yaakov, ותגיד לבני ישראל *koh
somar l'veis Yaakov v'sageid livnei Yisrael*, תאמר לבית יעקב Yaakov, אלו הנשים
*somar l'veis Yaakov eilu hanashim*, the women were there at הר סיני
*Har Sinai*. So there's a lot of statements about obviously the you
know about women's place in learning תורה *Torah*, but there are then
this point about the sort of technical exemption from the מצוה *mitzvah*
of תלמוד תורה *Talmud Torah*, which has a lot of ink has
been spilled on it in the modern era around that and around
how one deals with that and how one deals with the statement
in סוטה *Sotah* of כאילו מלמדה תפלות *k'ilu melamdah tiflus*, drawing lines
between תורה שבכתב *Torah she'bichsav* and תורה שבעל פה *Torah she'be'al peh*,
making distinctions between maybe not a technical מצוה *mitzvah* of לימוד תורה
*limud Torah* purely for its own sake, but you have to learn
all the תורה *Torah* that's relevant for the מצוות *mitzvos* and you
know there's tons of מצוות *mitzvos* to do, so that's tons of
תורה *Torah* and you have to learn תורה *Torah* as part of
your basic relationship to to הקדוש ברוך הוא *Hakadosh Baruch Hu* and
to religious life, so there's an enormous amount of תורה *Torah* you
have to learn there as well. So once you're done with all
of that, you know, the idea of women's obligation to learn תורה
*Torah* can wind up being, you know, not much different than that
of men. It does become interesting when both men and women want
to be spending their time sitting and learning their whole time and
having the other spouse sort of support them. Anyway, a lot to
be said about that, but this is the core גמרא *Gemara* on
which many many debates and discussions have been had. תנו רבנן *Tanu
rabanan*. Okay, let's keep on going. הוא ללמוד בנו ללמוד *Hu lilmod
b'no lilmod*. Similar to the previous question before. You know, it's either
you know you you you weren't educated yourself and you only have
and one person only has so much money or somebody has to
stay home and earn a living, so it's either you or your
son. Who is going to to get the opportunity to go learn?
Okay, הוא ללמוד ובנו ללמוד הוא קודם לבנו *Hu lilmod u'vno lilmod
hu kodem livno*. You come before your son. Okay, remember that was
the same opinion about פדיון הבן *pidyon haben*, take care of yourself
first.
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda Omer, *Rabbi Yehuda omer*. Now you remember
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* by פדיון הבן *pidyon haben* said
I mean the גמרא *Gemara* made it. What's he going to
say by תלמוד תורה? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, אומר, אם בנו זריז
וממולח תלמודו מתקיים בידו ותלמודו מתקיים בידו בנו קודמו. im beno zariz
ummulach tamudo mitkayem beyado u’tamudo mitkayem beyado beno kodmo. So he actually
agrees. He says there, you know, that you have a slightly greater
obligation, but ultimately you have to be thinking about who's going to
be more successful. So if you and your son will equivalently be
successful in your learning of תורה, you take care of yourself before
your son. You do have precedence. But if you see your son
is going to be better than you, he's, you know, he's sharp
and he's able to retain the knowledge, and he's got subtlety, so
then he takes precedence. כי הא דרב יעקב בריה דרב אחא בר
יעקב. ki ha d’Rav Yaakov brei d’Rav Acha bar Yaakov. So רב
יעקב Rav Yaakov the son of רב אחא, Rav Acha, the son
of יעקב, Yaakov. so יעקב, אחא, Acha, יעקב. Okay, so anyway, so
רב יעקב, Rav Yaakov, שדריה אבוה. shadrei avua. רב אחא Rav Acha
sent his son רב יעקב, Rav Yaakov, לקמיה דאביי, l’kamei d’Abaye, to
אביי Abaye to learn. כי אתא, ki ata, when he came, חזי
דלא הוו מחדדין שמעתיה. chazi d’lo havi mechadidun shmatai. So when he
came to check up on his son, he saw that his son
was not—didn't have the idea so sharp in his mouth. His son's
learning was not so great. אמר ליה, amar lei, אנא עדיף מינך.
ana adif minach. He said, "I can learn better than you. תוב
את דאיזיל אנא." tuv at d’eizal ana. You go, you stay home,
I'm going to go learn. Okay, so once he realized—so now that's
a little different than רבי יהודה because that sort of sounded like
actually the earlier רבי יהודה, that he defaulted his son. The question
is when they're exactly equal. This story sounds like he assumed his
son has an obligation and when he realized he was better, he
took precedence. That's different from saying, "I am obligated to myself but
when I realize my son is better then my son takes precedence."
Anyway, okay. שמע אביי דקא הוי אתי. shama Abaye d’ka havi ati.
So אביי Abaye heard that רב אחא Rav Acha was coming, the
father. הוי הוא מזיק בבי רבנן דאביי. havi hu mazik b’bei rabbanan
d’Abaye. Now there was a certain מזיק, mazik, like מזיקין, mazzikin, like
you know, an evil spirit in the ישיבה Yeshiva of
אביי. Abaye. דכי הוו עיילי בתרי אפילו ביממא הוו מיתזקי. d’chi havi
ailei bitrei afilu biyemama havi mitzkei. That when two people would come
in, even during the daytime, when you're supposed to be with another
person and in the daytime מזיקין mazzikin aren't supposed to bother you,
but in this בית מדרש beit midrash the מזיקין mazzikin were still—were
strong and, you know, this one מזיק mazik and it was—and it
was causing problems. So אמר להו, amar lehu, לא ליתיב ליה איניש
אושפיזא. lo laseiv lei inish ushpiza. Nobody should give רב אחא Rav
Acha a place to sleep. אפשר דמיתרחיש ניסא. efshar d’mitracheish nisa. He'll
be forced to sleep in the בית מדרש beit midrash and maybe
a miracle will occur. על, so he went to the בית מדרש,
beit midrash, this רב אחא, Rav Acha, because nobody gave him a
place to sleep. בת בו בבי רבנן. bat bo b’bei rabbanan. He
slept in that ישיבה. Yeshiva. אידמי ליה כתנינא דשבעה רישוותיה. idmi lei
k’tanina d’shiva rishvasei. So the מזיק mazik appeared to him like a
snake with seven heads. כל כריעה דכרע. kol kria d’kara. Every time—so
רב אחא Rav Acha was דאוונינג davening to God, you know, to
destroy the מזיק, mazik, and every time he bent—he bowed down, so
נתר חד רישיה. nassar chad reishei. One of the heads of this
snake-like מזיק mazik came off.
אמר להו למחר. amar lehu lemachar. So he said to the rabbis,
you know, or to the ישיבה Yeshiva students the next day, אילו
לא איתרחיש ניסא סכינתן. ilo itrachish nisan sakintan. If a miracle had
not occurred to me, you would have endangered me. I have no
idea how this is relevant to the story of him and his
son and so on. Okay, but anyway some really important גמרות Gemaras
about parental obligations, which are basically father's obligations to sons, ברית מילה,
פדיון הבן, teaching תורה, obviously major issues about what it means that
women are exempt from תלמוד תורה, and also really interesting questions about
a parent's obligation to their child and their obligation to themselves and
how to think out about the balancing of the two.